Guide to the Walter Blair papers, 1933-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Walter Blair papers 1933-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Blair, Walter, 1900-
3.0 Linear Feet Approx. 1350 Items
Walter Blair (1900-1992) was a professor at the University of Chicago from 1929 to 1968 and a specialist in American folklore and humor.
Collection contains early drafts, edited manuscripts, and proofs of Blair's publications, as well as bibliographic information and correspondence regarding publication of materials and other professional services. The bulk of the material is comprised of draft manuscripts of his work which he wrote with Hamlin Hill (Texas A&M), America's Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury (Oxford, 1978). There is also a smaller amount of other materials such as correspondence and reviews related to other publications, including Native American Humor: 1800-1900 (1937), Horse Sense in American Humor (1942), Tall Tale America: A Legendary History of Our Humorous Heroes (1944), Half-Horse Half-Alligator: The Growth of the Mike Fink Legend (1956), and Mark Twain and Huck Finn (1960). Forms part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for Literary Historiography.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter Blair papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1980-1981.
Biographical Note
Walter Blair (1900-1992) was a professor at the University of Chicago from 1929 to 1968. His research focused on American folklore, humor, and tall tales, and he is considered a pioneer in the field of American humor studies. Blair graduated from Yale University in 1923 and received his Ph.D. in English from the University of Chicago in 1931. He served as chair of his department from 1951-1960 and won the Distinguished Scholar Award of the Mark Twain Circle in 1992, as well as the Jay Hubbell Award from the American Literature Section of MLA. He was the author of many publications, including Native American Humor: 1800-1900 (1937), Horse Sense in American Humor (1942); Tall Tale America: A Legendary History of Our Humorous Heroes (1944); Half-Horse Half-Alligator: The Growth of the Mike Fink Legend (1956); Mark Twain and Huck Finn (1960); and American Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury (co-author with Hamlin Hill, Oxford, 1978).
Collection Overview
This collection contains early drafts, edited manuscripts, and master proofs of Blair's publications, including American Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury (co-authored with Hamlin Hill of Texas A&M, Oxford, 1978), which makes up the bulk of the Writings Series, as well as manuscripts of, reviews of, and correspondence regarding his earlier publications, including Half Horse Half Alligator, Horse Sense in American Humor, Mark Twain and Huck Finn, and Mike Fink: King of the Mississippi Keelboatmen. The collection also contains several reviews of Blair's publications. Biographical information and related materials, including newspaper clippings, magazine articles and newsletters regarding Walter Blair, and various professional correspondence comprises the remainder of the collection. Among the biographical information is a series of humorous Christmas cards that Blair circulated among his acquaintances, as well as a special issue of Studies in American Humor in honor of Blair. The bulk of the correspondence is comprised of letters to and from various university presses regarding publication of Blair's manuscripts, and letters to colleagues at various universities also regarding his manuscripts and other professional services.
Forms part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for Literary Historiography.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Blair, Walter, 1900---Humorists, American
Blair, Walter, 1900---Manuscripts
Folklore -- American
Publishers and publishing -- Correspondence
Tall tales -- American
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
Wit and humor -- American -- 18th century
Wit and humor -- American -- 19th century
Wit and humor -- American -- 20th century
Wit and humor, Pictorial
Correspondence -- American authors
Jay B. Hubbell Center for Literary Historiography (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Biographical Information and Other Materials Series, 1942-1986 and undated, (4 folders)
  Contains various newspaper clippings, magazine articles and newsletters concerning Walter Blair, including a special issue of Studies in American Humor in Blair's honor. Also contains an entry on Blair in Who's Who and a series of cartoons and Christmas cards he circulated among his acquaintances.
  - Articles, magazines, and newsletters, 1942-1986 (Box 1)
  - Christmas cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Studies in American Humor: Special Issue in Honor of Walter Blair, 1975 Apr. (Box 1)
  - Who's Who entries, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1974-1987, (5 folders)
  Contains primarily professional correspondence with various presses regarding publication and with colleagues at various universities regarding professional services.
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
- Writings Series, 1933-1980 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Contains early drafts and master proof manuscripts of Blair's writing. Drafts of chapters for America's Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury makes up the bulk of the material in this series, but the series also includes drafts of Blair's earlier publications. In addition, the series includes correspondence regarding publication of these materials.
  - America's Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury, 1975-1980 and undated
    - Preliminary pages and index, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Outlines, blurbs, chronology, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Early draft: "No End of Jokes," undated (Box 1)
    - Early draft: "Franklin," 1975 (Box 1)
    - Early draft: "John Wesley Jarvis," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Tall Tales and a Tough Demigod," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Davy Crockett and Mose the Fireb'hoy," undated (Box 2)
    - First draft: "The Big Bear of Arkansas," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Tall Tales and Go West," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Twilight of the Comic Demigod," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Local Colorists and Phunny Phellows," undated (Box 2)
    - Early draft: "Mark Twain," undated (Box 2)
    - Early drafts: "Mass Production Comic Demigod"; "The Lunatic Fringe: James Thruber," "The Secret Life of Walter Mitty," undated (Box 2)
    - Early drafts: "Humor in Fiction"; "Great American Novel"; Afterword, undated (Box 2)
    - Part 1, Starters: "No End of Jokes," undated (Box 2)
    - Part 1, Starters: "A Harmonious Human Multitude," undated (Box 2)
    - Part 1, Starters: "Cast Typing," undated (Box 2)
    - Part 2, The Golden Age of American Humor: "A National Phenomenon: The Reputables," undated (Box 2)
    - Part 2, The Golden Age of American Humor: "Subversives"; "Two Masterpieces"; "Tall Tales Go West," undated (Box 2)
    - Part 3, And the War Came: "Changes in Jokelore"; "Phunny Phellows," undated (Box 3)
    - Part 4, Mark Twain: "Mark Twain's Chestnuts"; "Mark Twain Pioneers," undated (Box 3)
    - Part 5, Into the Twentieth Century: "The Turn of the Century: Between World Wars," undated (Box 3)
    - Part 5, Into the Twentieth Century: "Modern Humor," undated (Box 3)
    - Part 5, Into the Twentieth Century: Afterward, References, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 3)
    - Illustrations, 1668-1977 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - America's Humor from Poor Richard to Doonesbury, Master proof, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Master proof: index, undated (Box 5)
  - Other Publications
    - Half Horse Half Alligator, reviews, 1956-1958 (Box 5)
    - Horse Sense in American Humor, reviews, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
    - Mark Twain and "Huck Finn", correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 5)
    - Mike Fink: King of the Mississippi Keelboatmen, reviews, 1933-1936 (Box 5)
    - Native American Humor, reviews, 1937 (Box 5)
    - Tall Tale America, correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - Tall Tale America, reviews, 1944-1945 (Box 5)